柏林,1933年2月
你就这点本事?
You're good at that, huh?
吓一群中国小女孩?
Scaring a handfulof little Chinese girls
你为什么在桌子下面?
Why are you under the table?
纳粹在追杀我
The Nazis are after me
纳粹?
The Nazis?
你好,麦克斯,你不是有点老成佐罗了吗?
Hello there, Max.Aren't you a bit old to be Zorro?
至少是一套服装,不像你!
At least it's a costume. Unlike you!
- 好吧,那是你的意见 - 白痴
- Well, that's your opinion      - Idiot
嘿,把我的兔子还给我!
Hey, give my rabbit back!
抓住!
Catch!
麦克斯,你给他看!
Max, you show him!
干掉他!
Finish him off!
你给他看看,麦克斯! 加油!
You show it to him, Max! Go on!
基于朱迪斯克尔的小说
Based on the novel by Judith kerr
元首偷走了
粉兔子
德国/瑞士 剧情/家庭/历史
- 我们不给乞丐 - 你这个无情的人!
- We don't give to beggars      - You heartless person!
你对一个可怜的乞丐孩子没有怜悯吗?
Have you no pityfor a poor beggar child?
- 还有一个饥饿的佐罗? - 不是直接进入客厅
- And a hungry Zorro?      - Not straight into the living room
快点,把湿衣服脱了
Come on, take off your wet things
麦克斯把他们都打倒了
Max knocked them all down
牛仔,印第安人...
The cowboys, the Indians...
以及纳粹
And the Nazis
- 是的! - 太棒了,麦克斯
- Yes!      - That was great, Max
我很高兴你玩得开心
I'm glad you had fun
开始了
Here we go
你们两个怎么这么湿?
How did you both get so soaking wet?
我们下了雪橇山
We went down the sledding hill
- 穿上暖和的衣服,在床上 - 好的
- Put on something warm. It's on the bed      - Okay
- 你的脸颊像只老狗 - 谢谢
- You have cheeks like an old dog      - Well, thank you
医生又来了吗?
Did the doctor come again?
他说你父亲需要再卧床三天
He said your fatherneeds to stay in bed three more days
他必须放松,不允许他工作
He has to take it easyand he's not allowed to work
或者去剧院
or go to the theater
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
- 香肠会淹死的 - 他们的时间到了
- The sausages will drown      - Their time is up anyhow
埃里希和奥托根本没有打扮
Erich and Otto didn't dress up at all
他们是纳粹分子
They just came as Nazis
他们和父母一样蠢
They're just as dumb as their parents
安娜,别这么厚脸皮
Anna, don't be so cheeky
- 嘉年华怎么样? - 很好
- How was carnival?      - Good
为什么在这里吃饭?
Why eat in here?
- 和海皮在一起很舒服 - 没错
- It's cozy in here with heimpi      - That's true
- 你要去另一场音乐会吗? - 是的
- Are you going to another concert?      - Yes
费舍尔小姐在唱舒伯特
Miss fischer is singing schubert
她要来接我了
She's about to pick me up
麦克斯,你的词汇书没碰过桌子
Max, your vocabulary bookis lying untouched on the desk
晚饭后,你学习
After dinner, you study
- Annuntio vobis gaudium: Habemus papam - 那是什么?
- Annuntio vobis gaudium: Habemus papam      - What's that?
说:"我们有教皇"
"We have a pope"
你疯了
You're crazy
多萝西娅·肯珀
Dorothea kemper
是的,我说
Yes, speaking
- 妈妈? - 我在和谁说话?
- Mama?      - Who am I talking to?
安静下来,完成那座山的土豆
Be quiet and finishthat mountain of potato
志龙,有丰富的语言
Silentium. Favete linguis
与犹太人战斗意味着除掉犹太人!
Fighting the Jew means removing the Jew!
你疯了吗? 我们是社会主义者,不是纳粹
Are you crazy? We're socialists, not Nazis
我们自己就是犹太人
And we're Jews ourselves
那你必须被移除!
Then you must be removed!
快走! 我得学习
Get lost! I have to study
你...坏了
You...spoilsport
海姆皮?
Heimpi?
他们没有权利
They have no right
妈妈? 你不是...
Mama? You're not...
- 出去! 关上门 - 但我...
- Out! Close the door      - But I...
- 我说出去! 现在! - 晚点再来亲爱的
- I said get out! Now!      - Come back later, honey
看上去很糟糕,我想妈妈在哭
It looked bad.I think mama was crying
不可能,妈妈从不哭,可能她在剥洋葱
No way. Mama never cries.Maybe she was peeling onions
当然,她在剥洋葱,我们的母亲! 穿着晚礼服
Sure, she was peeling onions.Our mother! Wearing an evening gown
出来,安娜,那里现在一定很冷
Out you come, Anna.It must be cold in there by now
在文学和戏剧中,邪恶有很多面孔...
In literature and theater,evil has many faces...
- 爸爸,你醒了吗? - 歌德的魔鬼玫瑰...
- Papa, are you awake?      - Goethe's devil Rose from...
过来,甜心
Come here, sweetheart
他是那个毫无防备的可怕幽灵...
He was the dreadful phantomof the unsuspecting...
别太靠近,我有传染性
Not too close. I'm contagious
梅菲斯托至少是个绅士
Mephisto was at least a gentleman
他亲自来向浮士德要他的灵魂
He came in personto ask faust for his soul
今天魔鬼只派他的仆人来
Today the devil just sends his servants
肮脏腐败,双手沾满血迹
Foul and corrupt,with blood-stained hands
尖叫和充满修辞,它要求德国的灵魂
screaming and full of rhetoric,it demands Germany's soul
收音机里是你吗?
Is that you on the radio?
是的,但你不用小声说话
Yes.But you don't have to whisper
我知道我上周说了什么
I know what I said last week
我不会投票给恶魔
I will vote no against evil
嘉年华怎么样?
How was carnival?
你也不应投他
So should you
太好了!
Great!
我是个乞丐女孩
I was a beggar girl
非常令人兴奋
It was very exciting
当你穷的时候甜甜圈味道更好
The donuts taste betterwhen you're poor
是真的,那是什么?
That's true. What's that?
一艘沉船
A shipwreck
一艘沉船?
A shipwreck?
冯太太告诉梅托画些漂亮的东西
Mrs. funk told meto draw something nice
你想画些好看的吗?
Do you want to draw something nice?
就像诅咒,除了灾难我什么也想不到
It's like a curse.I can't think of anything but disasters
这是有史以来最好的沉船
This is the best shipwreckanyone ever drew
你做得很好
You did a really good job
画这么阴郁的东西还不错吧?
It's not bad to draw such gloomy things?
如果你想画灾难,你应该画
If you want to draw a disaster,you should
画别人期望的东西是没有意义的
There's no point drawingwhat others expect
不会有用的
That won't work
麦克斯在派对上拿到的
Max captured this at the party
在古代,是好运的象征
In ancient times,the swastika was a good luck symbol
现在它变成了愚蠢的象征
Now it's reducedto a symbol of stupidity
扔掉它
Throw it away
安娜,你也会生病的
Anna, you'll get sick too
- 爸爸,我有时候很害怕 - 你害怕吗?
- I'm so scared sometimes, papa      - Are you?
你害怕什么?
What are you scared of?
雾和针
Of the fog and of the pin
妈妈刚才哭了
And mama was crying just now
你会被传染的乖女
You'll get infected, honey
不,我永远不会生病
No, I'll never get sick
有海姆皮照顾我
Heimpi takes care of me
当你生病的时候,你需要很多爱
When you're sick,you need a lot of love
爱是世界上最好的良药
Love is the best medicine in the world
哈利路亚
Hallelujah
你是个感情丰富的小东西
You're a very melodramaticlittle person
他妈的! 所有的雪都不见了
Damn! All the snow has gone
爸爸
Papa
爸爸!
Papa!
海皮!
Heimpi!
爸爸在哪?
Where is papa?
安娜!
Anna!
- 爸爸死了吗? - 没有
- Did papa die?      - No
麦克斯,你也来听一下
Max, you listen too
我要说的很重要
What I'm about to sayis very important
我们昨天接了个电话
We had a phone call yesterday
一个男人警告你父亲,是个警察
A man warned your father.A man from the police
- 所以你才不出去 - 没错
- That's why you didn't go out      - Exactly
警察里有很多纳粹分子,但这个人不是
There are lots of Nazis in the police,but this man isn't one
他认识爸爸也喜欢他
He knows papa and he likes him
欣赏他的报纸文章和著作
because of his newspaper articlesand his books
他打电话来告诉你爸爸的名字在名单上
He called to tell usthat papa's name is on a list
什么名单?
What list?
如果希特勒在十天后获胜
If Hitler wins the electionten days from now
他会对付那些反对者
he'll try to silencethose who are against him
那人说爸爸的护照会被拿走
The man saidthat papa's passport would be taken
他现在应该离开德国,而他仍然可以
and that he should leave Germany now,while he still can
离开? 但我们住在这里
Leave? But we live here
而且爸爸感冒了
And papa has the flu
他今天早上感觉好多了
He was feeling much better this morning
爸爸对那个人的担心很认真
Papa is taking that man's concernsvery seriously
今天一大早,他就去了捷克的布拉格
So very early this morninghe went to Prague, czechoslovakia
希特勒怎么知道爸爸受不了他?
How does Hitler knowpapa can't stand him?
所有人都知道
Everyone knows
他在报纸明确表明了反对立场
He states his opinionvery clearly in the paper
他在收音机里也说过
And he says it on the radio
- 而现在呢? - 我们将等待选举结束
- And now?      - We'll wait for the elections
如果希特勒胜出...
If Hitler wins...
我们去布拉格见爸爸
We'll go to meet papa in Prague
如果他输了,爸爸会回来的
And if he loses,papa will come back home
但我不想离开!
But I don't want to leave!
我也是
Neither do I
但听着
But listen
不能让任何人,任何人
Nobody, absolutely nobody
知道爸爸已经离开德国的事
can know that papa has left Germany
这很重要
That's very important
你不能告诉任何人
You mustn't tell anybody
- 格达和奥利呢? - 还有艾斯贝斯?
- What about Gunther and Oli?      - And elsbeth?
谁都不行,绝对不行!
Absolutely not. Nobody!
我也是犹太人
I'm Jewish too
- 从什么时候开始? - 一直都是
- Since when?      - Since forever
是吗? 我不知道
Really? I had no idea
我也不知道
Me neither
但你的鼻子甚至...
But your nose isn't even...
- 艾斯贝斯,不是每个... - 安娜?
- Elsbeth, not every...      - Anna?
你父亲还生病吗?
Is your father still sick?
- 是的,他得了流感 - 他已经病很长时间了
- Yes, he has the flu   - He's had that for a very long time
很奇怪,不是吗?
That's strange, isn't it?
他发烧多高?
How high is his fever?
我得回家了,我妈妈在等
I have to go home.My mother is waiting
祝他早日康复! 是的
Give him my best wishes! Yes
跟他说我想念他在报纸上写的...
Tell him I miss his articles in the paper...
那些刻薄的文章!
Those mean articles!
安娜!
Anna!
妈妈,什么事?
Mama. Yes?
兰贝克太太在外面...
Mrs. lambeck was outside...
- 你好,甜心 - 你好
- Hello, sweetheart      - Hello
- 朱利叶斯叔叔! - 安娜
- Uncle Julius!      - Anna
- 你为什么在这里? 你没有工作吗? - 今天没有
- Why are you here? Don't you have work?      - Not today
你在和我们一起吃饭吗?
Are you eating with us?
恐怕不行,我过来和你妈妈谈谈
I can't, I'm afraid.I stopped by to talk to your mother
我给你带来了这个
I brought you this
很漂亮,谢谢
It's beautiful, thank you
动物园里的大象怎么样? 太好了,他们不在乎希特勒
How are the elephants in the zoo?Wonderful. They don't care about Hitler
他们只是快乐的春天来了,所以他们可以回到外面
They're just happy spring is comingso they can get back outside
安娜,你的外套
Anna, your coat
我们该去看那个小家伙了
It's about timewe visited the little one
我敢打赌他现在都长大了
I bet he's all grown up now
吹来这里
Blow here
谢谢
Thank you
冈瑟能和我们一起吃饭吗? 他知道爸爸病了
Can Gunther eat with us?He knows papa is sick
不,爸爸需要绝对的休息,对不起,冈瑟
No, papa needs absolute rest.I'm sorry, Gunther
没关系的
That's all right
- 明天见,麦克斯 - 再见
- See you tomorrow, Max      - Bye
你父亲已经到布拉格了,朱利叶斯叔叔在那里见过他
Your father has arrived in Prague.Uncle Julius met him there
他不想我们再呆在这里
He doesn't want usto stay here any longer
- 我们明天在瑞士见他 - 明天?
- We'll meet him in Switzerland tomorrow      - Tomorrow?
海姆皮? 你想要这个吗?
Heimpi? Would you like this?
- 但是... - 我不能把这些东西都拿走
- But...      - I can't take all of this stuff
- 但这是不对的 - 当然
- But this isn't right      - Of course it is
他担心他们会拿走我们的护照
He's worried they'll take our passports
我们是他的家人我们是犹太人
We're his family and we're Jews
- 但不是合适的 - 没错
- But not proper ones      - Exactly
- 学校呢? - 还有海皮?
- What about school?      - And heimpi?
在我们都知道发生了什么之前我会处理好房子
I'll take care of the houseuntil we all know what's going on
如果纳粹赢了,你就来加入我们
If the Nazis win,then you'll come and join us
你毫无理由地打包这些东西
You're packing all this for no reason
两周后,我们将再次参观动物园
Two weeks from now,we'll all be visiting the zoo again
朱利叶斯,这些是第一版
Julius, those are first editions
有些是签名的,你能拿走吗?
Some are signed.Can you take them?
- 我会用我的生命守护他们 - 谢谢
- I'll guard them with my life      - Thank you
- 如果希特勒赢了,我们什么时候回来? - 没人知道
- If Hitler wins, when will we come back?      - Nobody knows
- 也许一个月,也许两三个月 - 三个月?
- Maybe in a month, maybe two or three      - Three months?
三个月没上学?
No school for three months?
我还不知道!
I don't know yet!
最重要的是我们不争论
The most important thingis that we don't argue
其次,我们必须打包,两本书一个玩具,就这样
Secondly, we have to pack.Two books and one toy, and that's it
第三,不要生病
And thirdly, don't get sick
我再说一遍,我们不会告诉任何人我们的计划
And I'll say this again.We're not telling anybody our plan
你们俩现在都有秘密要保密,这是一件很成熟的事情
You both have a secret to keep now.That's a very grownup thing
很艰难
This is tough
我爱你们所有人
I love all of you
如果我带走泰瑞,兔子会很伤心的
If I take Terri,the rabbit will be sad
如果我带走兔子,泰瑞会很伤心的
And if I take the rabbit,Terri will be sad
它们是填充动物,它们没有感情
They're stuffed animals,they don't have feelings
可惜我们不能参加棋盘游戏
It's a shamewe can't take the board games
我今年圣诞节才买的
I only just got them this Christmas
今年圣诞节我也有泰瑞
I got Terri this Christmas too
- 那就跟你一起去吧 - 但我养兔子这么久了
- Then take it with you      - But I've had the rabbit for so long
不管怎么说,你年纪太大了,不适合吃毛绒动物
You're too oldfor stuffed animals anyway
把你的铅笔留在这里,你可以同时拿两支
Leave your drawing pencils hereand you could take both
不可能!
No way!
好的,安娜,熄灯
All right, Anna, lights out
我不能选择,海皮
I can't choose, heimpi
我爱他们俩
I love them both
如果我留下一个,他们就不会明白
If I leave one behind,they won't understand
听我说
Listen to me
明天你走后
After you leave tomorrow
我再装一个手提箱,多装一个
I'll pack another suitcase,an extra one
我会把你的兔子和一些好书放进去
I'll put your rabbit in thereand some nice books
还有棋盘游戏
and the board games
当我知道你在哪里时,我会寄给你
When I know where you are,I'll send it to you
好吗?
All right?
你来的时候就带着吧
You could just bring it with youwhen you come
说吧,海皮
Say it, heimpi
晚安,亲爱的安娜,晚安,亲爱的麦克斯
Good night, dear Anna.Good night, dear Max
睡个好觉,做个好梦
Sleep well, sweet dreams
再见,直到明天
and goodbye until tomorrow
再见,海皮
Goodbye, heimpi
你能把你的大歌剧拍下来有点不公平
It's a bit unfair that you can takeyour whole huge opera
我们只允许一个玩具
and we're only allowed one toy
没有什么是不公平的,我在那部歌剧上干了两年
Nothing is unfair.I worked on that opera for two years
去穿好衣服
Go and get dressed
再见,办公室
Goodbye, office
再见,圆桌
Goodbye, round dining table
再见,大钢琴!
Goodbye, grand piano!
再见,亲爱的海皮厨房
Goodbye, dear heimpi kitchen
再见,可爱的老房子
Goodbye, lovely old house
他在哪?
Where is he?
海皮,你能看看房子吗?
Heimpi,could you take a look in the house?
- 是的 - 谢谢
- Yes      - Thanks
早上好!
Good morning!
去旅行? 那么一大早?
Off on a trip?So early in the morning?
我丈夫病得很厉害
My husband is so sick
我要送孩子和家人待在一起
that I'm sending the kidsto stay with family
那他就不能在星期天投票了
Then he won't be able to vote on Sunday
不,我想他不会的
No, I don't think he will
- 早上好,兰贝克夫人 - 早上好,麦克斯
- Morning, Mrs. lambeck      - Morning, Max
- 你去哪了? - 我得跟冈瑟道别
- Where have you been?      - I had to say bye to Gunther
你什么?
You what?
难以置信,快点,上车
Unbelievable. Come on, get in
再见,海佩尔小姐
See you soon, miss heimpel
再见,肯珀夫人
See you soon, Mrs. kemper
小心点
Take care
去吧,进去
Go on, get in
为了睡觉
For going to sleep
海姆皮
Heimpi
安娜
Anna
麦克斯
Max
143,144
143, 144
145...146...147
- 你在数什么? - 塔架
- What are you counting?      - The pylons
从莱比锡开始有150个...
Since leipzig there have been150...
想不出更愚蠢的事吗?
Couldn't think of anything more stupid?
我没什么可读的了,我完成了一切
I have nothing left to read.I finished everything
"名人
"Famous people"
你们必须在瑞士边境保持安静
You both must stay very quietat the Swiss border
- 为什么? - 你保证吗?
- Why?      - Do you promise?
如果他们问,就说我们要休假几天
If they ask,say we're vacationing for a few days
- 但是我们... - 没有但是!
- But we're...      - No buts!
我有一种奇怪的感觉
I have a strange feeling
别担心,闭上你的嘴,我们会没事的
Don't worry.Keep your mouth shut and we'll be okay
似乎每个名人都有一个非常艰难的童年
It seems like every famous personhad a very difficult childhood
我担心我们永远不会出名
I fear that we won't ever be famous
我等着瞧
I et's wait and see
爸爸!
Papa!
一切都好,亲爱的,我们快到边境了
Everything's okay, honey.We're nearly at the border
早上好,护照,谢谢
Good morning. Passports, please
麦克斯
Max
- 早上好 - 你要去哪里?
- Morning      - Where are you headed?
去苏黎世
To Zurich
我们在拜访亲戚
We're visiting relatives
你没有学校吗?
Don't you have school?
有人去世了
Somebody passed away
肯珀
Kemper
这个名字我很熟悉
The name is familiar to me
我从哪里知道的?
Where do I know it from?
我不知道,这不是一个不寻常的名字
I don't know.It's not an unusual name
是的,是的
Yes, it is
我整天都在绞尽脑汁
I'll be wracking my brains all day
旅途愉快,夫人
Have a good trip, madame
再见
Goodbye
麦克斯,请给我拿条毛巾
Max, please get me a towel
护照,谢谢
Passports, please
- 早上好 - 早上好
- Morning      - Good morning
谢谢
Thank you
小姐?
Young lady?
我能看看你的脸吗?
Can I see your face?
你看起来有点发烧
You look a little feverish
我感冒了
I have a cold
我们在这里说"鼻涕
We say "the sniffles" here
- 欢迎来到瑞士,夫人 - 谢谢
- Welcome to Switzerland, madame      - Thank you
谢谢
Thank you
你在燃烧
You're burning up
我太害怕了
I was so scared
我知道
I know
麦克斯
Max
金天鹅酒店,您好
Golden swan hotel, hello
你好
Hello
这是我妻子,欢迎,肯珀夫人
This is my wife.Welcome, Mrs. kemper
听着,我们可以把这个寄给海皮
Look. We can send this to heimpi
妈妈?
Mama?
- 我好渴... - 亲爱的!
- I'm so thirsty...      - Honey!
安娜?
Anna?
是什么? 安娜"?
What is it? Anna"?
小姐?
Young lady?
你能听到我说话吗?
Can you hear me?
她情况不好,她的体温超过104度
She's in a bad way.Her temperature is over 104
会导致大脑发炎
That can leadto inflammation of the brain
- 哪里可以买到? - 一家药店营业到午夜
- Where can I get it?      - One pharmacy is open until midnight
- 很远吗? - 没有
- Is it far?      - No
亚瑟
Arthur
海皮必须来
Heimpi must come
安娜?
So, Anna?
怎么了?
What's wrong?
海姆皮
Heimpi
吹,安娜
Blow, Anna
嘿,小家伙,你醒了吗?
Hey, little man. Are you awake?
我嗓子疼
My throat hurts
全国社会党赢得了288个席位
The national socialistshave won 288 seats
就像我说的,43.9%
Just like I said, 43.9 percent
希特勒将组成一个联盟
Hitler will form a coalition
德国人已经疯了
The Germans have lost their minds
我们现在怎么办?
So what do we do now?
我们不是要回柏林吗?
Aren't we going back to Berlin?
太冷了!
That's way too cold!
你回来了!
You're back!
我饿了
I'm hungry
你可以得到你想要的任何东西,什么都行
You can have anything you want.Anything at all
什么都行!
Anything!
我的爱人
My love
我很高兴你没死
Now I'm glad that you didn't die
最近这个房间里有大象吗?
Was there an elephantin this room recently?
是的,有,他坐在椅子上给你读书
Yes, there was.He sat in the chair reading to you
你不记得了吗?
Don't you remember?
奇怪,好像是真的
Strange. It seemed so real
你能再来一次小旅行吗?
Are you strong enoughfor another little trip?
我们现在要去哪里?
Where are we going now?
我们得走了,这家旅馆太贵了
We have to move.This hotel is too expensive
所以我们还不回家?
So we're not going home yet?
不是
Nope
希特勒没有赢得选举,但他获得了多数
Hitler didn't win the election,but he got a majority
- 我们还不能回去 - 我们要去乡下
- We can't go back yet      - We're going to the countryside
妈妈,他们来了!
Mom, they're here!
他们来了!
They're here!
欢迎来到zwirn宾馆
Welcome to the zwirn guesthouse
你好啊
Hello there
你好,我是弗兰兹
Hello. I'm Franz
你好,我是vreneli,这是我的妹妹特鲁迪
Hello. I'm vreneli.This is my little sister, Trudi
你好
Hello
现在是空的,但在夏天,客人大多坐在外面
It's empty now, but in summerthe guests mostly sit outside
当时灯亮着
The lights are on then
- 夏天我会去游泳 - 如果你学过,你这个笨蛋!
- In the summer I'll go swimming      - If you ever learn how, you dummy!
你明天会在学校加入我的班,对吗?
You'll join my class at school tomorrow,won't you?
麦克斯将和弗兰兹一起上高中
Max will go to high schoolin sils with Franz
小心,很热
Watch out, it's hot
好吃
Yummy
有你需要的一切吗?
Got everything you need?
土豆,啤酒?
Potatoes, beer?
泡菜?
Pickles?
好好吃饭吧
Enjoy your meal
闻起来像旧袜子
It smells like old socks
别抱怨了,吃光了
Stop complaining and eat up
- 但是海皮... - 但是海皮不在
- But heimpi would...      - Heimpi isn't here
这里是瑞士
This is Switzerland
如果你继续梦想德国,你会错过精彩的新事物
If you carry on dreaming of Germany,you'll miss wonderful new things
听着,妈妈喜欢
Look, mama likes it
她很喜欢
She loves it
我把狗带走了,真傻
It's silly that I took the dog
我想念我的兔子
I miss my rabbit
别再谈论你的动物了,我们还有其他问题
Stop going on about your animals.We have other problems
有吗? 像什么?
We do? Like what?
你有时候太幼稚了
You're so immature sometimes
在柏林,我在学校比你强
In Berlin I was more betterin school than you
不是"更好
Not "more better"
你的病花了我们不少钱
Your illness cost us a pretty penny
我们在那个昂贵的旅馆住了三个星期
We were in that expensive hotelfor three weeks
我病了三个星期?
I was sick for three weeks?
是的,你是
Yes, you were
医生也不便宜
The doctor wasn't cheap either
今天是什么日子?
What day is it today?
- 那是什么? - 日历
- What's that?      - A calendar
在我们回家之前,我会一个接一个地度过假期
I'll cross the days off one by oneuntil we go home
然后有趣地画十字架
Then have fun drawing crosses
妈妈说三个月...
Mama said three months...
如果爸爸不能卖东西,你就会在家里
If papa can't sell articles,you'll end up in a home
你这个骗子!
You liar!
我希望他们有别的东西,而不是融化的奶酪
I hope they have something otherthan melted cheese
这是来自德国的安娜,难民,她现在在我们班
This is Anna from Germany.The refugee. She's in our class now
欢迎,安娜
Welcome, Anna
听我说
Now, listen to me
安娜来自德国,不懂我们的语言
Anna is from Germanyand doesn't understand our language
我们都得慢慢地说清楚
We will all have to talkvery slowly and clearly
我是格劳普先生
I'm Mr. graupe
我来自说唱歌手
I'm from rapperswil
你呢?
And you?
你好,柏林
Hello. Berlin
你可以坐在罗西旁边的后面
You can sit at the back next to rosi
安静! 她怎么会知道?
Quiet! How is she meant to know?
准备好了吗? 我们又要去叫了
Ready? We're going to yodel again
我做错了什么?
What did I do wrong?
只有男孩可以从中间走下去
Only boys are allowedto walk down the middle
女孩们从边上走下去
Girls walk down the side
亚瑟!
Arthur!
小心!
Careful!
别那么快
Not so fast
简直是小菜一碟!
It's a piece of cake!
当你能说的时候,汉语也是如此
So is Chinese when you can speak it
- 在家爸爸知道怎么做每件事 - 嘿!
- At home papa knew how to do everything      - Hey!
那些日子结束了
Those days are over
朱利叶斯叔叔?
Uncle Julius?
朱利叶斯叔叔!
Uncle Julius!
你在这里干什么?
What are you doing here?
我在博尔扎诺的一个会议上想顺便来看看!
I was at a conference in bolzanoand thought I'd drop by!
他们是在选举后的一天到来的,正如你所预言的
They came one day after the election,as you predicted
他们想没收你的护照
They wantedto confiscate your passports
但海姆皮很勇敢
But heimpi was brave
她说她不知道你在哪,她把他们赶走了
She said she didn't know where you were,and she chased them off
好老海皮
Good old heimpi
你看到海皮了? 她好吗? 是的
You saw heimpi? Is she well?Yes
她让我帮她
She asked me to help her
什么?
With what?
上周二他们带着一辆卡车来拿你的东西
Last Tuesday they came with a truckand picked up your things
什么?
What?
钢琴也是?
The piano too?
他们全拿走了
They took it all
棕色的大行李箱?
The big brown suitcase?
我不知道,但他们拿走了一切
I don't know,but they took everything
并说它将在储存,直到你回来
and said it will be in storageuntil you return
我只有第一版的盒子
All I have is the box of first editions
至少你有,很好
At least you have that.That's good
- 如果你愿意,我可以卖给你 - 拉倒吧
- I can sell them for you if you want      - No way
从来没有
Never
你能去拿手提箱吗?
Could you go and get the suitcase?
- 里面有玩具,我们需要它们! - 这不是关于你的玩具
- It has toys inside. We need them!      - This isn't about your toys
我的兔子在那个手提箱里
My rabbit was in that suitcase
他们也烧了你的书
They burned your books too, you know
被那个肮脏的暴徒烧了? 我认为那是一种恭维
Burned by that filthy mob?I take that as a compliment
你想要一块吗?
Would you like a piece?
谢谢
Thanks
我喜欢泰瑞
I like Terri
他比那只老兔子漂亮得多
He's much prettier than that old rabbit
也许希特勒正在玩我的棋盘游戏
Maybe Hitler is playingone of my board games right now
我希望他对我的兔子很好
I hope he's nice to my rabbit
书燃烧后,图科尔斯基一直沉默不语
Tucholsky has been silentsince the book burning
我觉得他在流亡中很沮丧
I think he's depressed in exile
纳粹取消了他的国籍,他不会回来了
The Nazis revoked his citizenship.He's not coming back
你能在这里写字吗?
Can you write here?
是的,不是这个问题
Yes. That's not the problem
只是很难发表我的作品
It's just difficult to publish my work
为什么?
Why?
瑞士担心出版一本批评纳粹的书
Switzerland worriesthat publishing a critic of the Nazis
会让他们失去中立
would make them lose their neutrality
我觉得他们很害怕
And I think they're scared themselves
他们认为他们的小国家拥有太多的犹太知识分子
They think their little countryhas got too many Jewish intellectuals
你赚的钱够吗?
Are you making enough money?
我试着改变出版商的想法
I'll try and changethe publishers' minds
- 我能碰她吗? - 她害怕陌生人
- Can I touch her?      - She's afraid of strangers
你得小心点,没有快速动作
You have to be careful.No fast movements
你在这里很安全
You're safe here
- 那是最重要的 - 我不确定
- That's the main thing      - I'm not sure
或许我不该离开,德国需要我们的声音
Maybe I shouldn't have left.Germany needs our voices
你在开玩笑吗?
Are you joking?
还记得提特尔鲍姆教授吗?
Remember professor teitelbaum?
他们把他从大学带到营地
They took him from the universitystraight to the camp
他们把他放在狗窝里
Those swines put him in a dog kennel
附在铁链上
attached to an iron chain
他不得不爬上去
He had to crawl on all fours
从狗碗里吃他的食物
and eat his food out of a dog bowl
他睡在木屋的地板上
He slept chained up on the floorof a wooden hut
他每次都要吠叫,无论谁进出营地
He had to bark every timesomeone went in or out of the camp
否则他们会用棍子打他
or they'd beat him with sticks
链子太短了,他受不了
The chain was so shortthat he couldn't stand
两个月后他自杀了
He took his own life after two months
安娜,你心中有一束温暖的光
There's a small, warm lightburning in your heart, Anna
保护它
Protect it
不要让它被任何人或任何东西熄灭
Don't let it be extinguishedby anyone or anything
我们必须继续相信美好,这很重要
We have to keep believing in good.That's important
善总会赢
Good will always win
你能再给我吹一次吗?
Can you blow this openfor me again?
我不再相信了
I don't believe it anymore
你按了按钮
You're pressing the button
哦,我得走了
Oh. I have to go
朱利叶斯,保重
Julius, take care
剁碎,上床睡觉
Chop-chop. Off to bed
谢谢
Thank you
睡个好觉,做个好梦
Sleep well, sweet dreams
再见,直到明天
and goodbye until tomorrow
晚安
Good night
Night
米歇尔,我跟你说了什么?
Michel, what did I tell you?
- 你在看什么? - 没什么,我只是在找
- What are you looking at?      - Nothing. I'm just looking
你看,复古根本做不到
Look at that.Reto can't do it at all
- 不能做什么? - 车轮
- Can't do what?      - Cartwheels
- 我也能做得更好 - 谁在乎呢?
- Even I can do them better      - Who cares?
不管怎样,男孩都是傻瓜
Boys are dummies anyway
你需要更多的力量
You need more power
你得像这样伸展你的腿
You have to stretch your legs like this
明白了吗? 是的
Got it? Yes
很简单,你能做到的,别忘了你的腿
It's easy. You can do it.Just don't forget your legs
你需要更多的力量；!
"You need more power"!
给你!
There you go!
布雷尼,怎么了? 你很清楚
Vreneli, what's up?You know full well
我没有! 请告诉我
I don't! Please tell me
有一件事是肯定的
One thing is for sure
所有人都看到你的内裤了
Everyone saw your underwear
你现在是傻瓜了
You are the dummies now
他们来了!
They're coming!
那是什么?
What was that?
继续走
Just keep going
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
安娜,住手
Anna, stop it
快点,安娜
Come on, Anna
我警告你,如果你把这些都扔了...
I'm warning you now.If you throw all of those...
救命!
Help!
妈妈! 妈妈,救命!
Mama! Mama, help!
- 妈妈! - 怎么回事?
- Mamal!      - What's going on?
这一切都是什么? 雷托! 怎么回事?
What is all this?Reto! What's going on?
不! 雷托!
No! Reto!
在你告诉我之前我不会让你走的
I won't let you go until you tell me
出去! 告诉我!
Out with it! Tell me!
- 我们就是这么做的 - 那是什么?
- This is just what we do      - What's that?
向人们扔石头?
Throw stones at people?
因为我们爱她,我们这么做是因为我们爱她!
Because we love her.We did it because we love her!
什么?
What?
因为他们爱你
Because they love you
当他们喜欢某人时,他们会朝他们扔东西
When they love someonethey throw things at them
你应该感到荣幸
You should feel honored
- 好吧,那么 - 如果你是这么做的
- Okay, then      - If that's what you do here
小心,有东西要来了!
Watch out, something's coming!
谢谢,弗伦内尔
Thanks, vrenel
为了什么?
For what?
做我的朋友
Being my friend
我们很高兴你出生今天是你的生日
We're happy you were bornand that it's your birthday today
我们爱你,送你礼物
we love you and give you gifts
食物、乐趣和游戏
food and fun and games
我们很高兴你出生了,今天是你的生日
we're happy that you were bornand that it's your birthday today
亲爱的安娜
"Dear Anna
西奥多和我祝你有一个非常快乐和阳光明媚的一天；
Theodor and I wish youa very happy and sunny day"
大象宝宝不再是婴儿了,而是更像一个小学生了；
"The elephant baby isn't a baby anymore,but more like an elementary schooler"
从朱利叶斯叔叔那里向爱丽丝阿姨致以最良好的祝愿；
"Best wishes to aunt Alice,from uncle Julius"
- 谁是爱丽丝姑妈? - 他可能是指我
- Who is aunt Alice?      - He probably means me
他没有写我的名字是因为纳粹
He didn't write my namebecause of the Nazis
谢谢你! 很可爱,我把它和朱利叶斯叔叔的大象放在一起
Thank you! It's lovely.I'll put it with uncle Julius' elephant
当我十岁的时候,我有一辆自行车
When I was ten, I got a bike
会有更好的日子
Better days will come
今天下午我们要去苏黎世的汽船游览
We're going on a steamboat touron lake Zurich this afternoon
是吗? 是的
Really? Yes
它是由瑞士文学协会组织的
It's organizedby the Swiss literary society
我明白了
I see
- 会有其他孩子吗? - 不可能
- Will there be other kids?      - Unlikely
会有记者和出版商,可能对我们很重要
There'll be journalists and publishers.It could be important for us
安娜,快来! 德国的人在打电话
Anna, come quickly!Someone from Germany is on the phone
为了我? 是的
For me? Yes
喂?
Hello?
安娜,是你吗?
Anna, is that you?
海皮!
Heimpi!
安娜,祝你生日快乐
Anna, I wish youthe most wonderful birthday
海皮,我现在十岁了!
Heimpi, I'm ten now!
我知道,亲爱的,太不可思议了
I know, my dear.That's really and truly incredible
但你不必大喊大叫
But you don't have to shout
我不再是你的小安娜了
I'm not your little Anna anymore
不
No
你现在十岁了
You're ten now
你们都做得好吗?
Are you all doing well?
离开这里,去吧
Get out of here. Go
我们在吃蛋糕
We're eating cake
问她怎么得到号码的
Ask how she got the number
爸爸给我买了只山羊
Papa got me a goat
一只山羊? 你有花园吗?
A goat? Do you have a garden?
你从哪里得到我们的号码的?
Where did you get our number?
从朱利叶斯先生那里
From Mr. Julius
他给我的
He gave it to me
瑞士很美,海皮,快过来!
Switzerland is beautiful, heimpi.Please come soon!
我不能,我亲爱的孩子
I can't, my sweet child
我和另一个家庭有了新工作
I've got a new jobwith another family
好好照顾自己,好吗?
Take care of yourselves, all right?
海皮,说点什么
Heimpi, say something
- 20号飞艇快没了 - 我们要乘汽船去湖边!
- The 20 pfennig is nearly gone      - We're taking a steamboat on the lake!
是吗?
Really?
- 你好,海佩尔太太 - 你好
- Hello, Mrs. heimpel      - Hello from us
- 让我和海皮谈谈 - 你妈妈学会做饭了吗?
- Let me talk to heimpi      - Has your mother learned to cook?
男孩和女孩在学校分开,一切都和柏林不同
Boys and girls are separated at school.Everything's different than Berlin
安娜...
Anna...
即使你现在十岁了,你也永远是我的小女孩
Even though you're ten now,you'll always be my little girl
我永远不会忘记麦克斯...
I will never forget Max and...
现在她走了
Now she's gone
她找到了一个新家庭
And she found a new family
你邀请我来这里作为作家和戏剧评论家
You've invited me here to talkas a writer and theater critic
没有人为了好玩而流亡
Nobody goes into exile for fun
你喜欢你小时候的地方,喜欢人和语言
You love the place where you werea child, the people and the language
我一直认为当评论家是荒谬的
I always thoughtit was absurd to be a critic
如果批评是你所做的一切
if criticize was all you ever did
一年前,德国剧院开了花,种类繁多,富有
A year ago, German theaterwas blossoming, varied and rich
今天它是匮乏的,扭曲的,空洞的
Today it is wanting,distorted and hollow
我的工作是评估目前的状况
It is my job to assessits current state
甚至从我流亡的地方
even from my place in exile
我的广播讲话和新著作在德国遭到仇恨
My radio addresses and new writingsare met with hatred in Germany
但我无法阻止自己思考
But I can't stop myself from thinking
这一定是你过过的最无聊的生日
This must bethe most boring birthday you ever had
在柏林我的朋友会来拜访
In Berlin my friends would be visiting
海皮会做草莓蛋糕
And heimpi would make strawberry cake
你至少卖了一篇文章吗?
Did you at least sell an article?
不会那么快,安娜
It doesn't work that fast, Anna
但我谈得很好
But I had a few good talks
你知道什么? 你还没有十岁
Know what?You're not ten years old yet
为什么不呢?
Why not?
你1923年6月14日6：05在夏洛滕堡医院出生
You were born at 6:05 on June 14th 1923in charlottenburg hospital
我和你哥哥麦克斯在隔壁的酒馆吃肉丸
I was at the tavern next doorsharing meatballs with your brother Max
我们很紧张
We were very nervous
隔壁的酒馆? 麦克斯当时才三岁
The tavern next door?Max was only three then
我从没想过你的十岁生日会在瑞士的船上
I never imagined your tenth birthdaywould be on a boat in Switzerland
难道不能继续批评希特勒吗?
Isn't it dangerousto keep criticizing Hitler?
纳粹也能在这里找到我们
The Nazis could find us here too
我不想害怕,安娜
I don't want to be fearful, Anna
不管怎样,我们已经在逃亡了
And anyway, we're already on the run
你不介意当难民吧?
Don't you mind being a refugee?
我知道
I do
但我也觉得很有趣,你11岁的时候谁知道我们会在哪里
But I find it interesting too.Who knows where we'll be when you're 11
或者你127岁的时候
Or when you're 127
在家里?
at home?
我在这里赚不到钱,瑞士人不给我工作
I can't earn any money here.The Swiss won't give me work
我想我们得搬到另一个国家去
I think we'll haveto move on to another country
- 哪里? - 也许是巴黎
- Where?      - Maybe Paris
我可以写一篇犹太论文
There's a Jewish paperI could write for
巴黎? 麦克斯和我得学法语
Paris?Max and I would have to learn French
所以呢? 你的头很聪明
So what?You've a clever head on your shoulders
我想我不习惯做难民
I don't think I've got usedto being a refugee
我现在十岁了吗?
Am I ten now?
是的,刚好6：05
Yes. It's exactly 6:05
至少这意味着麦克斯和我有一天会出名
At least it meansthat Max and I can be famous one day
我们一定会有一个艰难的童年
We'll certainly havea difficult childhood now
你看? 一切都有好处
See? There's good in everything
- 你一个人能应付十天吗? - 当然
- Can you manage ten days alone?      - Sure
对吧,小家伙?
Right, little man?
如果我们喜欢巴黎找个公寓
If we like Parisand find an apartment
我们可能会早点回来
we might come back earlier
今晚我们要吃香肠
Tonight we're havingrosti with sausages
听兹维恩夫人的话,照她说的做
Listen to Mrs. zwirnand do what she says
她晚上会进来关灯
She'll come inand turn out the lights at night
你要好好表现,好吗?
And you'll behave yourselves, okay?
我每天给你写一张明信片
I'll write you a postcard every day
谢谢
Thank you
当你妈妈和我在巴黎的时候
While your mother and I are in Paris
你们两个将代表我们在瑞士的家人
you two will be representingour family in Switzerland
这是一个很大的责任
That's a big responsibility
为什么?
Why?
因为我们犹太人分散在世界各地
Because we Jews live scatteredaround the world
纳粹在散布关于我们的可怕谎言
and the Nazis are spreadingterrible lies about us
所以这对像我们这样的人来说很重要
So it's very importantfor people like us
证明他们是错的
to prove that they are wrong
我们该怎么做?
How do we do that?
比别人更诚实
By being more honest than others
更勤奋,慷慨和礼貌
more hard-working,generous and polite
我们得让人们知道做犹太人是件好事
We have to show peoplethat it's good to be Jewish
我相信等我们回来
I'm sure that when we get back
我们会为你代表我们感到骄傲的
we'll be very proudof how you represented us
- 好好保管好帽子,安娜 - 我会的
- Take good care of the hat, Anna      - I will
你,麦克斯
And you, Max
好好照顾安娜
take good care of Anna
再见
See you
- 你一定要回来? - 我们当然回来了!
- You're definitely coming back?      - Of course we are!
别忘了来接我们,别忘了我们!
Don't forget to come and get us.Don't forget us!
安娜,你疯了吗?
Anna, are you crazy?
我永远不会忘记我的孩子!
I'd never forget my children!
别吃那么多了,瓦利,你越来越重了
Stop eating so much, vali.You're getting heavier
如果我不吃,我会头晕,我已经头晕了
If I don't eat, I get dizzy.I'm dizzy already
快到了,瓦利,你能做到的!
Nearly there, vali.You can do it!
嘿,不要打架!
Hey, no fighting!
嘿,安娜
Hey, Anna
你爸爸今天在报纸上
Your dad was in the paper today
是吗? 所以他终于卖了一篇文章
Really?So he finally sold an article
不,不是那个
No, it wasn't that
上面说他们在找他
It said they're looking for him
阿道夫·希特勒甚至在他的头上付出了代价
Adolf Hitler has even puta price on his head
1000瑞奇马克
1000 reichsmark
但别担心
But don't worry
希特勒不能在这里碰他
Hitler can't touch him here
他在瑞士很安全
He's safe here in Switzerland
害怕新学校?
Scared of the new school?
可能是那种语言,但我还是理解了你
Of the language maybe.But I managed to understand you
不过,我会说德语
I speak German though
或多或少
More or less
那边那两个人也是德国人
Those two over thereare from Germany too
我知道,但他们不跟我玩
I know.But they don't play with me
他们是纳粹
They're Nazis
和他们玩是不是很糟糕?
Is it bad to play with them?
不
No
他们能在两周内回柏林真糟糕,我做不到
It's bad that they can go back to Berlinin two weeks and I can't
快醒醒! 是什么?
Wake up! "What is it?
是空的
It's empty
再也没有什么味道了
It doesn't smell of anything anymore
不,安娜,对不起,今天没有明信片
No, Anna, I'm sorry.There was no postcard today
什么都没有
Nothing
我们明天可能会有三个
We'll probably get three tomorrow
写你的远足,他们会喜欢的
Write about your hike.They'll like that
为什么要给别人的头定价,麦克斯? "什么?
Why put a price on someone's head, Max?"What?
格劳佩先生说希特勒给了爸爸一个代价
Mr. graupe said that Hitlerhad put a price on papa's head
当你答应给别人一个奖励,因为你找到了别人
It's when you promise someone a rewardfor finding someone else
我们已经知道希特勒在找他
We already knewHitler's looking for him
不管怎样,我希望爸爸现在在这里
Anyhow, I wish papa was here now
早上好,祝大家度过美好的一天
Good morning.I wish you all a wonderful day
谢谢
Thank you
快点
Come on
很勇敢,你觉得他们意识到你在开玩笑?
That was very brave.Think they realized you were teasing?
我没有,我是想表现得更有礼貌
I wasn't.I was trying to be extra polite
四处转转,加油!
Go around. Go on!
加油! 你抓不到我
Go on! You can't get me
是的,我会的,别担心
Yes, I will. Don't you worry
帮帮我! 小偷太快了!
Help me! The thief is too fast!
快走!
Go!
爸爸,我太怕你了!
Papa, I was so scared for your head!
我的头?
My head?
因为希特勒为此付出了代价
Because Hitler put a price on it
我也有点担心,你好,你
I was a little worried about that too.Hello, you
是吗? 是的
Really? Yes
1000马克对我这样的人来说很便宜,你不觉得吗?
1000 Mark is pretty cheapfor someone like me, don't you think?
我很想写希特勒的正式控诉书
I'm tempted to write Hitlera formal complaint
妈妈在哪?
Where is mama?
她在巴黎,修我们的公寓
She's in Paris,fixing up our apartment
我们的公寓? 是的
Our apartment? Yes
它有阳台和厨房
It has a balcony and a kitchen
剩下的我来做,太重了
I'll do the rest. It's too heavy
里面有一整块奶酪
There's a whole cheese in there
- 香肠、面包和煮鸡蛋 - 谢谢
- And sausages, bread and boiled eggs      - Thank you
- 在路上喝点东西 - 谢谢
- Something to drink on the road      - Thank you
孩子们,下来
Kids, get down
好好照顾,你在这里总是受欢迎的
Take good care.You're always welcome here
谢谢你,兹韦恩夫人,为了一切
Thank you, Mrs. zwirn.For everything
再见
Goodbye
- 弗兰兹 - 再见
- Franz      - Goodbye
安娜在哪里"?
Where is Anna"?
我很难过你要走了,你是我最好的朋友
I'm sad that you're leaving.You're my best friend
你不也难过吗?
Aren't you sad too?
是的,我是,但作为一个难民你经常说再见
Yes, I am.But as a refugee you often say goodbye
这是我艰难童年的一部分
It's part of my difficult childhood
安娜,快点! 我们得走了
Anna, come on! We have to go
看看我在练习什么
Look what I've been practicing
太好了,维尼利!
Great, vreneli!
再见,狭窄的小巷
Goodbye, narrow alleys
再见,大石头
Goodbye, big rock
再见,老水坑
Goodbye, old watering hole
再见,笨蛋!
Goodbye, dummy!
再见,安娜
Bye, Anna
听着
Look
是埃菲尔铁塔
It's the Eiffel Tower
建造它的人不是埃菲尔,而是波尼克豪森
The man who built itwasn't called eiffel, but bonickhausen
法国人说不出伊索他们叫他埃菲尔
The French couldn't pronounce itso they called him eiffel
因为他来自埃菲尔地区
because he was from the eifel area
他们也不会发音
They can't pronounce that either
我以为是黄色的
I thought it was yellow
为什么?
Why?
- 因为爸爸说它有阳台 - 所以它必须是黄色的?
- Because papa said it has a balcony      - So it had to be yellow?
一种漂亮的颜色,至少
A nice color, at least
按下按钮
Press the button
晚上好,教授
Good evening, professor
晚上好
Good evening
所以...这些是你的孩子?
So...these are your kids?
是的,这是麦克斯和安娜
Yes, this is Max and Anna
多可爱啊,晚上好,小家伙
How cute. Evening, little one
我给你买了些糖果
I bought you some candy
过来,菲菲!
Come here, Fifi!
谢谢
Thanks
- 不客气 - 谢谢
- You're welcome      - Thanks
等等
Wait a moment
请在这里签名
Please sign here
- 什么? - 授权
- What is it?      - The authorization
- 什么授权? - 当然是我的
- What authorization?      - Mine, of course
使一切井然有序
So that everything is in order
太好了
Perfect
- 我们有电梯吗? - 是因为我们现在有钱了吗?
- Do we have an elevator?      - Is that because we're rich now?
快点
Come on
- 亲爱的! - 妈妈
- My darlings!      - Mamal
是的!
yes!
- 你终于来了! - 我好想你
- You're finally here!      - I missed you so much
兹韦恩太太给了我们一整块巧克力蛋糕
Mrs. zwirn gave us a wholechocolate cake to take with us
- 你好 - 你好,先生
- Hello      - Hello, sir
快进来
Come on in
我想知道是什么感觉
I wonder what it's like
这是你的房间,黄色的
This is your room, the yellow one
黄色是如此美好,快乐的颜色
Yellow is such a nice, happy color
为什么这里这么黑?
Why is it so dark in here?
你有这盏漂亮的小灯
You have this nice little lamp
- 还不错 - 到客厅来
- It's not so bad      - Come into the living room
厨房也是
It's the kitchen too
不错
Nice
- 这就是你所谓的阳台? - 是的,对我来说,这是个阳台
- This is what you called a balcony?      - Yes. For me, this is a balcony
- 谁住在这里? - 仆人
- Who used to live here?      - The servants
很舒服
It's cozy
这是你的房间吗,爸爸?
Is this your room, papa?
是的
Yes
这是我的办公室
This is my office
厕所呢?
And the bathroom?
厕所在楼梯间
The toilet is in the stairwell
我们和邻居分享
We share it with the neighbor
我给你一碗温水洗
I'll give you a bowl of warm waterto wash with
谁是我们的邻居?
Who is our neighbor?
她叫格雷特
She's called grete
她是来自奥地利的女孩
She's a girl from Austria
她是来学法语的
She's here to learn French
她有点...奇怪,但她会说德语
She's a little...strange,but she speaks German
她也是犹太人吗?
Is she Jewish too?
- 土豆! - 不太可能
- The potatoes!      - Unlikely
- 哦,不 - 你睡在哪里?
- Oh, no      - Where will you sleep?
我给你看点东西
I'll show you something
麦克斯,帮帮我,抓住并拉
Max, help me out.Take a hold and pull
快点,还有沃伊拉
Come on. And voila
神奇的沙发!
A magic sofa!
小心,开始了
Watch out. There we go
- 我把所有东西都烧了 - 没事的
- I burned everything      - It's okay
我们比在zwirns还有一个房间
We have one more roomthan we did at the zwirns
我以为会更好
I thought it would be nicer
我也是
Me too
我尽力了
I tried my best
但这里的炉子很难控制
But the stove here is hard to control
鸡蛋味道很好
The egg tastes good
但土豆有点黑
But the potatoes are a little dark
烧死了
Burned
无所谓
It doesn't matter
尝尝这个
Try this
你可以生活在奇妙的奶酪,面包和葡萄酒
You can live wonderfullyon cheese, baguette and wine
巴古特?
Baguette?
这是法语的"棍子
It's French for "stick"
把那个给我
Give me that
嘿,别太过分
Hey, not too much
我觉得情况不妙
I think it's gone bad
- 已经发霉了 - 是圣牧
- It's moldy already      - It's a Saint maure
山羊奶酪在灰烬中翻滚
Goats cheese rolled in ash
我们到的每一个地方,都有旧奶酪
Every place we end up,there's old cheese
好像是
Seems so
我为我们的家人干杯
I drink to our family
以及我们在这个城市的未来
and to our future in this city
干杯
Cheers
听起来...很流利
That sounded...very fluent
- 干杯 - 干杯
- Cheers      - Cheers
你能在这条河里游泳吗?
Can you swim in this river?
是的,但不是这里
Yes, but not here
这条河叫做围网
The river is called the seine
快点
Come on
塞纳河...你好...干杯
Seine...hello...cheers
我已经知道这三个单词是法语了
I already know these three wordsin French
我们不能允许我们的评论
We can't allow our reviews
伤害移居国外的德国艺术家
to harm emigrated German artists
我们的评论是严肃的,但不是严厉的
Our reviews are seriousbut not scathing
我们要求你委婉一点
We request you to be tactful
你是柏林最害怕的评论家
You were Berlin's most-feared critic
我不想让我的德国同胞生活艰难
It's not in my interestto make life hard for my fellow Germans
我更喜欢给予普拉塞坦轻蔑
I much prefer giving praisethan giving scorn
是吗?
Really?
你愿意为我们每周写一次信吗
Would you be preparedto write for us once a week
关于巴黎剧院的场景?
about the Parisian theater scene?
我想做更多
I'd love to do even more
我们想给你更多,但我们负担不起
We'd like to give you more,but we can't afford it
文化现在是一种奢侈
Culture is a luxury now
最后!
Finally!
- 怎么样? - 很好,爸爸有工作
- How was it?      - Good. Papa has work
是吗?
Really?
- 那是我的 - 我也可以吗?
- That's mine      - Can I have one too?
我们在这里吃饭吗? 我饿了
Are we eating here? I'm hungry
一周复习一次,15法郎,每月60法郎
One review a week for 15 francs.That's 60 francs a month
我能给你拿点什么吗?
Can I get you anything?
我们要怎么生活?
How will we live on that?
不用了,谢谢,我们要走了
No, thanks. We're going
让你妹妹吃点
Let your sister have some
- 我们家里只有面包和... - 奶酪
- All we have at home is bread and...      - Cheese
回家的路上我们去买黄油和鸡蛋
We'll get butter and eggson the way home
又是鸡蛋?
Eggs again?
是的,又是鸡蛋
Yes, eggs again
快点,我们走
Come on, let's go
我把这一半留给你了
I left this half for you
- 麦克斯? - 我需要一个新书包,一个法国书包
- Max?      - I need a new schoolbag, a French one
以及长裤
And long pants
- 我明白了 - 其他男孩怎么样了?
- I see      - How was it with the other boys?
不知道,我一整天都听不懂一个字
No idea.I didn't understand a word all day
当我不会说这种愚蠢的语言时,我怎么能结交新朋友?
How can I make new friendswhen I don't speak this stupid language?
学习语言的最好方法是通过音乐
The best way to learn a languageis through the music
住手,你让我难堪了
Stop it. You're embarrassing me
快点
Come on
安娜,过来!
Anna, come!
- 你不能站在你这边吗? - 你为什么需要这么多空间?
- Can't you stay on your side?      - Why do you need so much space?
我不能集中精力在你的涂鸦上
I can't concentrate with you scribbling
- 那就去别的地方 - 我得学习
- Then go somewhere else      - I have to study
- 在地板上画你那愚蠢的画 - 麦克斯
- Draw your stupid pictures on the floor      - Max
麦克斯能上学而我不能上学是不公平的
It's unfairthat Max can go to school and I can't
一所私立学校就够了
One private school is enough expense
那我就去一所非私立学校
Then I'll go to a non-private school
很简单的人就会把他们的孩子送到那里
That's where very simple peoplesend their kids
我们现在也是普通人
We're simple people too now
他们甚至不教拉丁语
They don't even teach Latin there
我们可能很穷,但你的教育是第一位的
We might be poor,but your education comes first
怎么了?
Now what?
我得集中精神
I have to concentrate
我真希望我有个妹妹
I wish I had a sister
但愿我没有
I wish I didn't
我也太大声了吗?
Am I also too loud?
没关系的
It's okay
我能和你待一会儿吗?
Can I stay with you for a while?
你又吵了吗?
Did you argue again?
你的灾难怎么样?
How are your disasters?
他们会死于雪崩吗?
Will they all die in the avalanche?
恐怕是的
I'm afraid so
你有时间去问礼宾要邮件吗?
Do you have time to goand ask the concierge for the mail?
安娜,你听到了吗?
Anna, did you hear me?
是的,是的
Yes, I did
我害怕楼梯间
I'm scared of the stairwell
我明白了
I see
好吧,这次我和你一起去
Okay, I'll come with you this time
但明天你一个人做
But tomorrow you'll do it alone
很好,快点
Good. Come on
- 你好,格雷特小姐 - 你好
- Good day, miss grete      - Good day
为什么她总是这么奇怪?
Why is she always so strange?
我不知道,也不想考虑
I don't knowand I don't want to think about it
你找到你喜欢的工作了吗
Did you find a jobthat's to your liking
肯珀教授先生?
Mr. professor kemper?
是的,普伦夫人,我在巴黎一家报纸工作
Yes, madame prune,I work for a Paris newspaper
你不用担心房租
You don't have to worry about the rent
很高兴听到这个消息
Pleased to hear it
一份移民文件,是吗?
One of those immigrant papers, is it?
想要橄榄吗?
Want an olive?
- 很多犹太人在那里找工作 - 希望如此
- Lots of Jews find work there      - I hope so
快点,安娜
Come on, Anna
别忘了房租每周到期
Don't forgetthat the rent is due every week
- 星期五! - 明白了
- Fridays!      - Got it
亲爱的安娜,这只可爱的兔子让我想起了你的粉红色兔子
"Dear Anna, this lovely harereminded me of your pink rabbit
你在美丽的巴黎城市过得怎么样?
How are you doingin the beautiful city of Paris?
你已经试过蜗牛在大蒜黄油里了吗?
Did you alreadytry snails in garlic butter?
爱丽丝姨妈不久前给了我一些聪明的建议
Aunt Alice gave mesome smart advice a while ago
有时候我觉得我应该接受它
Sometimes I thinkthat I should have taken it
朱利叶斯叔叔的爱；
Lots of love from uncle Julius"
什么建议?
What advice?
你真的能吃蜗牛吗?
Can you really eat snails?
他不该回德国
He shouldn't have gone back to Germany
我一直告诉他
I kept telling him
我看起来糟透了
I look terrible
我的头发!
My hair!
你要去哪里?
Where are you going?
亚瑟,不!
Arthur, no!
太贵了!
It's far too expensive!
我不想要,不!
I don't want any. No!
亚瑟,回来
Arthur, come back
住手!
Stop it!
- 搞定了! - 真的? 所有的练习?
- Done!      - Really? All of the exercises?
- 好的,好的 - 我马上就到
- Yes, yes      - I'll be right there
太棒了!
Excellent!
- 你好,我能帮你什么吗? - 你好,夫人
- Hello, how can I help you?      - Hello, madame
铅笔
Pencil
我想"老板娘"是给女人的
I think "madame" is for a woman
是的
That's right
谢谢
Thank you
铅笔
Pencil
谢谢,不客气
Thanks. You're welcome
两法郎
Two francs
非常感谢
Thank you very much
还有...再见
And...goodbye
再见
Goodbye
什么都没有了? 妈妈说我们可以留着零钱
There's nothing left?Mama said we could keep the change
- 没关系,快点 - 这很重要!
- It doesn't matter. Come on      - It does matter!
便宜,便宜...
Cheap, cheap...
很便宜!
Cheap!
便宜的铅笔?
Cheap pencil?
谢谢
Thank you
是的,是的,明白了
Yes, yes. Got it
谢谢,不客气
Thanks. You're welcome
我们现在有20美分,想想我们能买到什么!
We have 20 cents now.Think of what we can buy with that!
可能不是很好
Probably not very much
再见,夫人
Goodbye, madame
我看那个胡桃夹子!
I ook at that nutcracker!
闻起来像格鲁尼沃德
It smells like grunewald
我希望今年我们有一棵圣诞树
I hope we havea Christmas tree this year
当然!
Of course!
我亲爱的朋友
My dear friend
你的明信片是黑暗地平线上的光芒
Your postcards are rays of lighton an otherwise dark horizon
你是唯一一个从家里听到的人
You are the only one from back homewhom we hear from
所有的妓女,爱因斯坦,老人...
All of the hauptmanns,einsteins, oldens...
他们现在在哪里?
Where are they now?
我不禁怀疑过去他们是否会离开
I can't help wonderingif in the past they would have left
我的一封信没有回复
a letter from me unanswered
当然不是
Surely not
我从没想过我会写这个
I never thought I would write this
但恐怕我得请你卖几个我们的第一版
but I'm afraid I must ask you to sella few of our first editions
我被剥夺了德国国籍
I've had myGerman citizenship taken away
现在我主要是一件事：犹太人
Now I'm primarily one thing: A Jew
至少这意味着我们不属于被误导的群众或纳粹暴徒
At least that means we don't belongto the misled masses or the Nazi mob
犹太人是有经验的移民
And Jews are experienced emigrants
尽管很痛苦
And although it's painful
我很高兴属于一个有着如此丰富遗产的民族
I'm happy to belong to a peoplewith such rich heritage
爸爸? 我想我得上去
Papa? I think I have to go up there
不,你可以坐在这里
No, you can sit down here
肯珀先生?
Mr. kemper?
肯珀先生? 我不是故意吓你的
Mr. kemper?I didn't mean to startle you
你还记得我吗?
Do you remember me?
恐怕我没有
I'm afraid I don't
罗伯特·斯坦
Robert Stein
从剧院来的
From the theater
完全正确,是那个
Exactly. That's the one
你好
Hello
- 我不知道你在巴黎 - 我妻子在这里有家人
- I didn't know you were in Paris      - My wife has family here
在柏林我再也没有工作了,我们一年前来的
There's no more work for me in Berlin.We came a year ago
这是我女儿安娜
This is my daughter Anna
- 你好,安娜 - 你好
- Hello, Anna      - Hello
如果你在那里,我们住在第七区
If you're ever there,we live in the 7th arrondissement
也许你和你的家人可以过来喝茶
Maybe you and your familycould come over for tea
柏林现在是古老的历史
Berlin is ancient history now
我很乐意花时间和这么聪明的人在一起
I'd love to spend timewith such a brilliant mind
谢谢
Thank you
我会联系你的
I'll be in touch
- 再见 - 再见
- Goodbye      - Goodbye
- 再见,安娜 - 再见
- Goodbye, Anna      - Bye
爸爸,你不喜欢那个人吗?
Papa, don't you like that man?
我没有理由不去
I have no reason not to
但我想他可能不喜欢我
But I thought he might not like me
我们在犹太教堂撞见了罗伯特·斯坦
We bumpedinto Robert Stein at the synagogue
罗伯特·斯坦?
Robert Stein?
- 你把他撕成碎片了 - 很对
- You tore him to pieces a few times      - Very true
他是个很没天分的导演
He's an intensely untalented director
他的作品令人难以忍受
His productions were unbearable
我以为他很好
I thought he was nice
我的工作不是找出他有多好
It wasn't my job to find outhow nice he was
他很坏就是这样
He was bad and that's that
如果你这么说那一定是真的
And if you say so then it must be true
是的
That's right
你太傲慢了
You're so arrogant
他看起来并不十分怨恨
He didn't seem very resentful
他妻子也是个钢琴家吗?
Wasn't his wife a pianist too?
他邀请我们喝茶,他们住在一个非常奇特的地方
He invited us to tea.They live in a very fancy area
野马不能拖着那个业余爱好者
Wild horses couldn't drag meto that amateur
谢谢你,妈妈
Thank you, mama
不客气
You're welcome
很漂亮
It's beautiful
- 他们确实是套头衫 - 没错
- They really did turn out as pullovers      - Indeed
有人怀疑他们会吗?
Did somebody doubt they would?
过来,这是给你的
Come here, this is for you
太漂亮了
That's beautiful
给我看看
Show me
用你的拇指滑过去
Flick through with your thumb
太神奇了,你是怎么做到的?
It's amazing. How did you do it?
麦克斯,看
Max, look
不错啊,小家伙!
Not bad, little man!
我不想给你更多的灾难
I didn't want to give youany more disasters
这是书包吗?
Is this a school bag?
你妈妈给你找了所公立学校
Your mother founda public school for you
我觉得那些学校对我们这样的人不好
I thought those schoolswere bad for people like us
谁说的这么胡说八道?
Who says such nonsense?
很难想象
That's hard to imagine
你怎么...
How did you...
我没偷,那是肯定的
I didn't steal them, that's for sure
多萝西娅?
Dorothea?
我还有别的东西给你
I have something else for you
所以你不会忘记你是谁
So you don't forget who you are
圣诞快乐
Happy Christmas
谢谢
Thank you
一个气球
A balloon
亲爱的安娜
"Dear Anna
我最衷心的祝愿度过一个美好的圣诞节
my most heartfelt wishesfor a wonderful Christmas
把这个气球从埃菲尔铁塔上扔下来
Drop this balloon from the Eiffel Tower
西风一定会吹到我在柏林的前门
and the west wind is sure to blow itto my front door in Berlin
会让我开心的,我期待着充满希望的新的一年
That would make me happy.I look to the new year full of hope
事情可以而且必须变得更好
Things can and must get better
在那张纸条上...你的,朱利叶斯；
On that note...yours, Julius"
圣诞快乐,格雷特小姐!
Happy Christmas, miss grete!
晚上好
Good evening
如果我们是犹太人,为什么要庆祝圣诞节?
If we're Jewish,why do we celebrate Christmas?
我把它看作是德国的庆典而不是基督教的庆典
I see it as a German celebrationrather than a Christian one
它让我想起了美妙的家庭聚会
It reminds meof wonderful family gatherings
当我像你这么大的时候
when I was your age
你相信上帝吗?
Do you believe in god?
恐怕不行
I'm afraid not
我只相信感恩
I only believe in gratefulness
不感恩的人总会失去
People who don't feel gratefulalways lose
我现在非常感激,尤其是我的书包
I'm very grateful right now,especially for my school bag
你来自哪里?
Where are you from?
安娜,你要呆多久?
Anna, how long will you stay?
你明白吗? 你的裙子太短了
Do you understand?Your skirt is too short
你有小妹妹吗? 你为什么穿她的外套?
Do you have a little sister?Why are you wearing her coat?
你需要一套制服,我带你去哪里买
You need a uniform.I'll show you where to get one
拿破仑的胜利：
Napoleon's victories:
1800马伦戈
1800 marengo
奥斯特里茨
1805 austerlitz
1806耶拿
1806 jena
1807弗里德兰
1807 friedland
1809字谜
1809 wagram
很好,你可以坐下来
Very good. You can sit down
他最后一次失败是在滑铁卢,那是在1815年
His final defeat was in Waterloo.That was in 1815
是真的,他们是这么说拿破仑的吗?
That's true.Is that all they said about Napoleon?
有那么多有趣的事情
There are so many interesting things
整节课都是学习日期
The whole lessonwas just learning the dates
- 你好,爸爸,嗨,小家伙 - 你好
- Hi, papa. Hi, little man      - Hello
- 怎么样? - 很好,我今天拿到制服了
- How was it?      - Good. I got my uniform today
明白了吗?
Understand anything yet?
- 不,但数学很简单 - 很好
- No, but math is easy      - Very good
至少是这样
That's something at least
- 你已经看起来像法国人了 - 是好是坏?
- You look French already      - Is that good or bad?
- 我不知道 - 你好
- I don't know      - Hello
又是土豆汤?
Potato soup again?
- 里面至少有肉吗? - 你每天都问同样的问题
- Is there meat in it at least?      - You ask the same thing every day
我想电影院是不可能的?
I guess cinema is out of the question?
这是第一次有同学邀请我
It's the first timemy classmates invited me
但我打赌我不能去,是吗?
But I bet I can't go, can I?
好吧,那你来决定!
Okay, then you decide!
要么我们明天吃顿热饭,要么你和你的朋友去看电影
Either we have a hot meal tomorrowor you go to the cinema with your pals
我们只能做一个或另一个,我们该怎么办?
We can only do one or the other.So, what do we do?
事情会永远这样吗?
Will things stay like this for ever?
他们抓到我们了
They've got us
- 纳粹 - 你这傻东西
- The Nazis      - You silly thing
只是灯泡
It's just the lightbulb
麦克斯,你和我晚点再走
Max, you and I will take a walk later
又是两法郎
That's another two francs
- 所以你还是饿 - 我总是饿
- So you're still hungry      - I'm always hungry
在这等着
Wait here
- 我们不是应该买个灯泡吗? - 试试,很好
- Shouldn't we have bought a lightbulb?      - Try it, it's good
给你,先生
Here, monsieur
谢谢
Thank you
孩子们! 告诉你爸爸两天前房租到期了
Kids! Tell your dadthe rent was due two days ago
星期五
On Friday
他在德国出名吗,你爸爸?
Was he famous in Germany, your dad?
- 你们是犹太人吗? - 是的,我们是犹太人
- Are you Jews?      - Yes, we're Jews
你不在德国了,这里是巴黎,明白了吗?
You're not in Germany anymore.This is Paris. Understood?
典型的!
Typical!
奇怪的人,像小偷一样爬来爬去
Strange people,creeping around like thieves
对吧,菲菲? 犹太人
Right, Fifi? Jews
不深
It's not deep
但太冷了
But it's so cold
- 你在干什么? - 我要进去了
- What are you doing?      - I'm getting in
这是不允许的
That's not allowed
不管怎样,他们中的大多数都变绿了
Most of them have gone green anyway
太疯狂了,安娜
This is crazy, Anna
别像个傻瓜一样盯着我,帮我一把
Stop staring at me like a dummyand give me a hand
你好,贝蒂夫人
Hello, madame batier
你好,姑娘们
Hello, girls
光!
Light!
没人能想象他会变成什么样
Nobody could have imaginedwhat would become of him
他的母亲叫拉蒂西亚
His mother was called laetitia
- 你怎么拿到钱的? - 拿破仑想得到承认
- How did you get the money?      - Napoleon wanted recognition
- 我们只是稍微蘸了一下 - 但她从来没把他当回事
- We just took a little dip      - But she never took him seriously
他在学校表现出色
He excelled at school
在一个令人难以置信的年轻时代成为了领导者
and became a leaderat an incredibly young age
他赢得胜利后
He won victory after victory
甚至被加冕为皇帝,并使他的兄弟姐妹成为国王和王后
was even crowned emperorand made his siblings kings and queens
但他母亲总是说："让我们看看它能持续多久；
But his mother always said,"let's see how long it lasts"
结果不太好
And it didn't turn out well
如果她表现出对他的骄傲会有不同吗?
Would it have been differentif she'd shown pride in him?
拿破仑是如此有趣的话题
Napoleon is such an interesting topic
他总是喜欢看起来像他母亲的女人
He always fell for womenwho looked like his mother
但他妈妈当然不喜欢他们
But his motherdidn't like any of them, of course
你怎么知道这一切的?
How do you know all this?
我刚才又读了一遍
I read up on it again just now
- 我在写他童年的剧本 - 看电影?
- I'm doing a script about his childhood      - For a movie?
如果有人买了它,那么它可能会变成电影
If someone buys it,then it might get made into a movie
晚安
Good night
你知道拿破仑的事吗?
Do you know things about Napoleon?
是的,他身上没有音乐的骨头
Yes, he didn't havea musical bone in his body
他唯一喜欢的就是鼓和小号
The only thing he likedwere drums and trumpets
但他一直记得有一个科西嘉托儿所押韵
But there was a corsican nursery rhymethat he always remembered
爸爸又做噩梦了
Papa is having nightmares again
让我睡吧
Let me sleep
但我很害怕
But I'm scared
你睡不着吗?
Can't you sleep?
格雷特是纳粹吗?
Is grete a Nazi?
或许吧
Maybe
也许她只是不喜欢犹太人
Perhaps she just doesn't like Jews
就像普鲁恩夫人
Like madame prune
- 会有食物吗? - 当然,不要太大声
- Will there be food?      - Certainly. Don't be too loud
好好表现,好吗?
Be on your best behavior, okay?
对
Right
- 肯珀夫人,真可爱 - 斯坦夫人,谢谢你的邀请
- Mrs. kemper, how lovely      - Mrs. Stein, thanks for the invitation
快进来
Come inside
我很高兴接到你的电话
I was so pleased to get your call
我一整天都觉得无聊透顶
I get so incredibly bored all day
来吧
Come
汉娜,古斯塔夫,我们的客人来了!
Hannah, Gustav, our guests are here!
仅仅因为我们的丈夫不成熟,并不意味着我们必须如此
Just because our husbands are immature,it doesn't mean we have to be
- 不是吗? - 是的
- Isn't that so?      - Indeed
我很高兴有柏林来的客人
I'm thrilledto have visitors from Berlin
我丈夫从来不是个人的意思
My husband never meant it personally
他非常喜欢戏剧,有时他...
He loves theater so muchthat sometimes he...
肯珀夫人
Mrs. kemper
罗伯特被你丈夫写的东西伤得很深
Robert was incredibly hurtby what your husband wrote
但我相信最终它帮助了他的发展
but I'm sure that in the endit helped him develop
你丈夫现在在做什么?
What is your husband working on now?
他在写关于拿破仑的剧本
He's writing a script about Napoleon
他现在有时间
He has time right now
拿破仑? 多有趣啊
Napoleon? How interesting
如果你吃完了,你可以离开桌子
You can leave the tableif you're done
谢谢
Thank you
我带你看看我的房间
I'll show you my room
- 你要利口酒吗? - 当然
- Would you like a liqueur?      - Certainly
它适合我吗? 我会穿在高尔夫球场上
Does it suit me?I'll wear it on the golf course
多么迷人的主意啊! 你看起来像个牛油杯
What a charming idea!You look like a buttercup
你后面会有成群的蝴蝶
You'll be followedby swarms of butterflies
而你,我最亲爱的心,就像灯罩
And you, my dearest heart,look like a lampshade
想吃什么就吃什么,反正我们有太多了
Take whatever you like.We have too much anyway
如果你不这样做,它就会捐给穷人
If you don't,it'll be donated to the needy
我们也很需要
We're needy too
我们也有很多我们已经读过的德语书
We also have lots of German booksthat we already read
你知道怎么读书,不是吗?
You know how to read, don't you?
看书?
Read?
你什么意思? 我们的父母不相信教育
What do you mean?Our parents don't believe in education
你会把这些都还给我的!
You'll give that all back!
我的孩子不需要施舍,当然不是那个小丑!
My kids don't need handouts.Certainly not from that clown!
我们不是乞丐!
We're not beggars!
你知道你的孩子需要什么吗?
Do you know what your kids need?
他们需要食物和衣服
They need food and clothes
还有各种各样的东西
and all kinds of things
我不能少管我们从哪里得到它
And I couldn't care lesswhere we get it
你不再是住在格鲁尼瓦尔德的著名评论家了
You're not a famous criticliving in grunewald anymore
那些日子结束了
Those days are over
如果衣服是给可怜的孩子穿的
If the clothes were meantfor poor children anyway
为什么不把它们给我们的?
why not give them to ours?
我不会把裤子还给你,你不必这么做
I'm not giving these pants back.You don't have to
我们现在穷吗?
Are we poor now?
- 很好,曼农 - 谢谢
- Very good, manon      - Thank you
安娜,147个错误
Anna, 147 mistakes
你得更加努力
You have to work harder
否则你就不会上下一节课了
or you won't move up to the next class
你明白吗?
Do you understand?
罗莎莉,很好
Rosalie, good
安娜,你的鞋子很漂亮
Anna, you have very pretty shoes
- 凯瑟琳,很好 - 谢谢
- Catherine, very good      - Thanks
伊莎贝尔,注意逗号
Isabelle, watch your commas
一年前,他失去了在自然历史博物馆的工作
A year ago, he lost his jobat the natural history museum
我不知道
I didn't know that
你好
Hello
这是我们的女儿安娜,朱利叶斯是她的教父
This is our daughter Anna.Julius was her godfather
安娜,这是海因兹罗森菲尔德,朱利叶斯的朋友之一
Anna, this is heinz rosenfeld,one of Julius's friends
- 柏林 - 你好
- From Berlin      - Hello
你就是安娜
So, you're Anna
朱利叶斯不想让你担心
Julius didn't want you to worry
继续
Carry on
很长一段时间他表现得很好
He was doing fairly wellfor a long while
他每天去动物园参观他的动物
He went to the zoo every dayand visited his animals
他每周在一家卷烟厂干两次家务活
He did menial workin a cigarette factory twice a week
朱利叶斯知道我会去巴黎,我有家人在这里
Julius knew I would go to Paris.I have family here
他死了吗?
Is he dead?
当他们禁止他进入动物园后,他变得阴郁起来
After they banned him from the zoo,he became gloomy
他不会再离开他的房间了
He wouldn't leave his room any more
朱利叶斯是犹太人吗?
Was Julius Jewish?
他祖母是
His grandmother was
看来这对他们来说已经足够了
It seems that was enough for them
他很累
He was tired
他不想再活下去了
He didn't want to live anymore
但你收到这个对他很重要
But it was very important to himthat you receive this
你可以在两个主题之间进行选择
You can choose between two topics
"旅程；
"A journey"
和"在海滩上的一天
and "a day at the beach"
你可以开始了
You can start
亚瑟,这毫无意义
Arthur, that's pointless
如果她今天找不到我们,她明天就回来
If she doesn't find us today,she'll come back tomorrow
明天我可能有钱,我现在不想和她打交道
Tomorrow I might have money.I don't want to deal with her right now
我们不在这里,灯不亮
We're not hereand the light stays off
我们还会在哪里?
Where else would we be?
也许只是格雷特
Maybe it's only grete
只有格雷特? 她甚至...
Only grete? She's even...
肯珀先生?
Mr. kemper?
别胡说了,开门!
Stop this nonsenseand open the door!
- 我知道你在那儿! - 如果我们...
- I know that you're there!      - If we...
当他们让像你这样的人进来的时候就会这样
This is what happenswhen they let people like you in
骗子!
Liars!
我在盯着你,肯珀先生!
I have my eye on you, Mr. kemper!
你不付钱就不会超过我
You won't get past me without paying
肮脏的犹太人
Dirty Jew
那是有辱人格的
That's degrading
14,15,16,17,18...
14, 15, 16, 17, 18...
谢谢你,夫人
Thank you, madame
夫人,为什么我的考试有钱?
Madame, why is there money on my test?
哦,对了,我完全忘了
Oh, right, I'd completely forgotten
孩子们,听我说
Children, listen to me
安娜一年前才到,一个字也说不出法语
Anna arrived only a year agoand couldn't speak a word of French
她的拼写仍有一些需要改进的地方
Her spelling still leavesomething to be desired
但她的论文赢得了学校比赛
but her essaywon the school competition
穆林先生为她的旅行故事给了她十法郎
Mr. moulin awarded her ten francsfor her journey story
我们该怎么说?
What do we say?
安娜,请到前面来大声朗读你的故事
Anna, please come to the frontand read your story out loud
旅程,安娜·肯珀
"A journey". By Anna kemper
那是一个寒冷的二月夜
"It was a cold February night
亚瑟得了重感冒
Arthur had a bad cold
他应该呆在床上
He should have stayed in bed
突然电话响了
Suddenly the telephone rang
"我是朋友"声音说
I'm a friend, ' the voice said
我得警告你
'And I have to warn you.'
我的针线活失败了
I failed needlework
但我在运动方面做得很好
but I did really well in sport
我们不得不单腿站立两分钟
We had to standon one leg for two minutes
很简单
That was easy
所以要善于站在一条腿上为你的缝纫做准备?
So being good at standing on one legmakes up for how you sew?
只在女子学校!
Only at a girls' school!
谁从英国给爸爸写信?
Who's writing to papa from england?
你好,格雷特小姐
Hello, miss grete
然后呢? 好吗?
And? Is it good?
当然
Absolutely
我是班上的佼佼者,好极了
I'm top of my class. "Wonderful
安娜的一条腿上站着一枚金牌
Anna got a gold medalfor standing on one leg
别傻了,实际上我赢了一些钱
Don't be stupid.I won some money actually
为什么?
What for?
- 我写了你的旅行 - 给我看看
- I wrote about your journey      - Show me
你们犹太人总是最好的,不是吗?
You Jews always have to be the best,don't you?
- 你有来自英国的邮件 - 谢谢
- You have mail from england      - Thanks
- 我给你读我的故事好吗? - 拜托
- Shall I read you my story?      - Please do
数学不容易,但我也得了18分
Math wasn't easy,but I got 18 points there too
只有我和七年级的一个男孩能做到
Only me and one boyin the 7th managed that
是吗? 我有这么聪明的孩子
Really?I have such clever children
安娜·肯珀的旅程；
"A journey by Anna kemper"
- 他们想买 - 谁想买什么?
- They want to buy it      - Who wants to buy what?
拿破仑,英国人想买我的剧本
Napoleon.The english want to buy my script
他们也付了不少钱
They're paying good money too
哇,太棒了!
Wow, this is amazing!
你会头晕
You get dizzy
小心!
Watch out!
亲爱的气球,飞到柏林,祝你好运
Dear balloon, fly to Berlin.Good luck
你觉得它能到柏林吗?
Think it will make it to Berlin?
也许它不需要
Maybe it won't have to
我觉得朱利叶斯很接近
I think Julius is very close
听着,已经结束了,拿破仑的坟墓
Look, it's already over les invalides,Napoleon's tomb
敬朱利叶斯,我的朋友
To Julius, my friend
现在?
Now?
是的
Yes
我们考虑搬到伦敦去
We've thought about moving to London
只是这里的工作不够
There's just not enough work here
你在开玩笑吗?
Are you joking?
我刚开始喜欢这里
I've only just started to like it here
有了这个剧本...
And with this script job...
我们可以去伦敦看看能否找到一套公寓
We could go ahead to Londonand see if we can find an apartment
你可以在学校上两个星期
You could board at school for two weeks
不,我们不能!
No, we can't!
你不能把我们单独留在巴黎一天!
You can't leave usalone in Paris for a single day!
但是安娜...
But Anna...
父母有时不得不让他们的孩子独处一段时间
Parents sometimes have to leavetheir children alone for a short while
在英国,许多孩子上寄宿学校
In england many childrengo to boarding school
那些孩子有家我们没有!
Those kids have a homeand we don't!
如果你没有家,你必须呆在一起!
If you have no home,you have to stay together!
否则你会迷路的
Otherwise you get lost
我同意,小家伙
I agree, little man
别这么叫我! 我不小也不是男人
Don't call me that!I'm not small and I'm not a man
我们能永远不回家吗?
Can we never go back home?
我不知道
I don't know
或许有一天
Maybe one day
但现在不行
But not now
或许我们永远不会在一个地方待在家里
Maybe we'll never be at homein one single place
但在许多不同的地方有点在家
but a little bit at homein many different places
可能也不错
That could be nice too
嗯...
Well...
不好意思
Excuse me
再见,格雷豪斯
Goodbye, gray house
再见,拉维考瓦
Goodbye, rue de la victoire
把那个给我,我把它放在后面
Give me that. I'll put it in the back
- 你好亚瑟 - 你好
- Hello Arthur      - Hello
我有话想说
There's something I wanted to say
你对普鲁恩夫人说了什么?
What did you say to madame prune?
在我和她之间
That's between me and her
那是英语,明白什么吗?
That's english.Understand anything?
一句话也不说
Not a word
我们又回到原点了
We're back to square one
我们谁都不认识,什么都不懂
We don't know anyoneand don't understand anything
英国人有什么奇怪的习俗?
What odd customs do the english have?
我等不及今晚在伦敦吃一块可爱的旧奶酪了
I can't wait to eat a lovely pieceof old cheese in London tonight
我一个字都不懂,但没关系
I don't understand a word,but it doesn't matter
因为很快,很快我就会明白这一切
Because soon,soon I will understand it all
1935年,朱迪丝克尔和她的家人移居英国
In 1935 Judith kerr and her familyemigrated to england
战后她学习艺术
After the war she studied art
作为儿童读物的插画家工作
and workedas an illustrator of children's books
她哥哥迈克尔学法律
Her brother Michael studied law
成为高等法院的第一位外国出生的法官
and became the first foreign-born judgeof the high court of justice
当希特勒偷走粉红色兔子时,被翻译成20种语言
"When Hitler stole pink rabbit"was translated into 20 languages
使朱迪丝·克尔闻名于世
and made Judith kerr world-famous
朱迪丝克尔于2019年5月在伦敦去世,享年95岁
Judith kerr died in may 2019at the age of 95 in London
她在那里找到了他渴望的家
There she had found the homeshe had longed for
阿尔弗雷德和朱迪丝克尔,1934年
Alfred and Judith kerr, 1934